<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-btw-add-rfc8484-clarification-00"
     ipr="trust200902" updates="8484">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DoH Redirection">Supporting Redirection for DNS
    Queries over HTTPS (DoH)</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Neil Cook" initials="N." surname="Cook">
      <organization>Open-Xchange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>neil.cook@noware.co.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560071</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>TirumaleswarReddy_Konda@McAfee.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Citrix">Citrix Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing-ietf@fuggles.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>ADD</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document clarifies whether DNS-over-HTTPS (DoH) redirection is
      allowed, describes potential issues with redirection in DoH, and
      proposes how DoH redirection might be performed.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document clarifies the intent of DNS-over-HTTPS (DoH) <xref
      target="RFC8484"></xref> whether redirection is allowed (<xref
      target="clarification"></xref>), potential issues with
      redirection in DoH (<xref target="redirection_issues"></xref>)
      and subsequently makes some proposals for how service-level
      (<xref target="service_level"></xref>) and resource-level (<xref
      target="resource_level"></xref>) redirection might be performed.</t>

      <t>This document adheres to Section 4.3 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-bcp56bis"></xref> which discusses the need for
      protocols using HTTP to specify redirect handling to avoid
      interoperability problems.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>"A/AAAA" is used to refer to "A and/or AAAA records".</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Discussion">
      <t><xref target="RFC8484"></xref> indicates that the support of
      HTTP <xref target="RFC7540"></xref>
      redirection is one of DoH design goals (Section 1):<list style="empty">
          <t>"The described approach is more than a tunnel over HTTP. It
          establishes default media formatting types for requests and
          responses but uses normal HTTP content negotiation mechanisms for
          selecting alternatives that endpoints may prefer in anticipation of
          serving new use cases. In addition to this media type negotiation,
          it aligns itself with HTTP features such as caching, redirection,
          proxying, authentication, and compression.</t>

          <t>The integration with HTTP provides a transport suitable for both
          existing DNS clients and native web applications seeking access to
          the DNS."</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Nevertheless, Section 3 of <xref target="RFC8484"></xref> indicates
      the following:<list style="empty">
          <t>"This specification does not extend DNS resolution privileges to
          URIs that are not recognized by the DoH client as configured
          URIs."</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This looks like an internal inconsistency of <xref
      target="RFC8484"></xref> that is worth the clarification: is redirection
      allowed or not?</t>

      <t>Also, Section 3 of <xref target="RFC8484"></xref> indicates that:</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>"A DoH client MUST NOT use a different URI simply because it was
          discovered outside of the client's configuration (such as through
          HTTP/2 server push) or because a server offers an unsolicited
          response that appears to be a valid answer to a DNS query."</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Nevertheless, <xref target="RFC8484"></xref> does not:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>specify under which conditions a discovered different URI can be
          used.</t>

          <t>describe how a different URI can be discovered using HTTP/2
          server push. The only available example in the mailing list archives
          clarifies that server push is an example of unsolicited responses.
          <vspace blankLines="1" />The text was updated late in the
          publication process to address this comment:
          https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/msg/doh/f_V-tBgB-KRsLZhttx9tGt75cps/.
          The example provided in the thread (server push) is related to the
          second part of the above excerpt.</t>

          <t>clarify that unsolicited messages from a trusted DoH server
          should be excluded.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>A clarification is proposed in <xref target="clarification"></xref>.
      This clarification focuses on a "different URI" that might be discovered
      while communicating with an HTTP server.</t>

      <t>Additionally, assuming that redirection is allowed, this
      specification recommends how it is achieved, specifically regarding
      inline resolution of any domain name in the redirect URI. This is
      required because redirection to a domain-based URI requires DNS
      resolution of that domain name, which creates a potential bootstrapping
      problem (e.g., If DoH server is the only configured DNS server,
      redirecting the client to a new server by presenting a name will
      fail).</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="clarification" title="RFC8484 Update">
      <t>OLD:<list style="empty">
          <t>A DoH client MUST NOT use a different URI simply because it was
          discovered outside of the client's configuration (such as through
          HTTP/2 server push) or because a server offers an unsolicited
          response that appears to be a valid answer to a DNS query.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>NEW<list style="empty">
          <t>A DoH client MUST NOT use a different URI that was discovered
          outside of the client's configuration when communicating with HTTP
          servers except via HTTP redirection from a configured URI (Section
          6.4 of <xref target="RFC7231"></xref>).</t>

          <t>Also, a DoH client MUST ignore an unsolicited response (such as
          through HTTP/2 server push) that appears to be a valid answer to a
          DNS query unless that response comes from a configured URI (as
          described in Section 5.3).</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="redirection_issues" title="Issues with Redirection in DoH">
      <t>There are several potential issues with redirection in DoH,
      which are summarized below.</t>

      <t>
        The first issue to be considered is whether a new document
        considering redirection is needed at all. Redirection in HTTP
        is done on a per-resource basis; if the only functionality
        required is to redirect all requests to an entirely different
        server under the same administrative control, then the
        alternative service mechanism described in <xref
        target="RFC7838"></xref> might be sufficient. However, there are
        restrictions on the use of alternative services; specifically
        the certificate presented by the alternative service must be
        valid for the origin. This restriction means that alternative
        services cannot be used for use-cases such as redirecting the
        client to a locally administered DoH server (e.g., resolver or
        forwarder) which does not have a certificate valid for the
        origin. Additionally, alternative services suffer from the
        bootstrapping issue described below.
      </t>

      <t>
        The second issue is that HTTP redirection is done on a
        per-resource basis; this presents several problems for DoH:
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>
          Every GET request with a new query name will require redirection,
          which is suboptimal. Indeed, a redirect will only affect a
          unique request, and the DoH client will thus need to contact
          the origin server for every new request and get
          redirected, requiring two roundtrips. Also, permanent
          redirects <xref target="RFC7538"></xref> for all these
          queries would bloat the client's HTTP cache.
        </t> 
        <t>
          Using POST requests would solve the issue. Nevertheless POST responses are
          not widely cached as per Section 4.2.3 of <xref
          target="RFC7231"></xref>, and mandating the use of POST
          requests for DoH in order to enable redirection hardly seems
          reasonable.
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        The final issue with using HTTP redirection is 
        bootstrapping; any client that is relying solely upon a DoH server
        for resolution must be able to resolve the domain in the
        redirect response.  Even if
        a DoH client has a plaintext DNS resolver configured, using that
        resolver is considered as a minimal privacy leakage <xref
        target="RFC8310"></xref>. One possible solution is for the DoH client
        to use the same server that returned the redirect response to
        perform the resolution, however that may then lead to a further
        redirect response. Another solution is for the DoH server to
        include additional information in the response, similar to the
        "glue" records as defined in <xref target="RFC7719"></xref>.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        The above issues would seem to indicate that despite the
        intention of <xref target="RFC8484"></xref> to align itself with
        HTTP redirection, some additional work is required in order for any
        other mechanism than alternative services (e.g., <xref target="RFC7838"></xref>)
        to be deployed with confidence.
      </t>

      <t>The rest of this document considers the issue of redirection at two levels:
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>
          Service-level Redirect: Similar to alternative services, this
          would allow a DoH server to redirect a DoH client to an
          alternative service for all future queries, rather than on a
          per-resource basis.
        </t>
        <t>
          Resource-Level Redirect: Solving the bootstrapping problem for
          regular HTTP redirects. Note that this doesn't solve the caching
          issues described above, and does raise the question of whether
          regular HTTP redirection is desirable or worthwhile
          (i.e., are there any valid use-cases for resource-level
          redirection in DoH?).
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </section>
      
    <section anchor="service_level" title="Service-Level Redirect">
      <t>
        We consider two possibilities for service-level redirect:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Extending <xref target="RFC7838"></xref> by relaxing the
            host authentication checks.
          </t>
          <t>
            Using the well-known URI specified in <xref
            target="I-D.pp-add-resinfo"></xref> to return information
            about alternative services.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <section anchor="extend_7838" title="Extending Alternative Services">
        <t>
          Section 9.2 of <xref target="RFC7838"></xref> discusses the
          possibilities for attackers to hijack the communication to an
          origin. This is the justification for the requirement in
          Section 2.1 of <xref target="RFC7838"></xref> that "Clients MUST have reasonable assurances that
          the alternative service is under control of and valid for the
          whole origin.".
        </t>
        <t>
          However, when a DoH server presents an alternative 
          DoH service to a DoH client, both the origin and alternative
          service, as well as the DNS queries and responses, must be, by
          definition, resistant to MITM attacks. Thus it could be argued
          that in these circumstances, relaxing the host authentication
          requirements is justified. The relaxation could be limited,
          e.g., still requiring some relationship between the origin and
          the alternative, or unlimited, allowing no such relationship
          to exist.
        </t>
        <t>
          The bootstrapping issues described in <xref
          target="redirection_issues"></xref> still apply, which may
          make this proposal unsuitable for wide deployment.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="well_known_uri" title="Well-Known URI">
        <t>
          Section 3 of <xref target="I-D.pp-add-resinfo"></xref>
          allows the use of a well-known URI to retrieve resolver
          information, which presumably could include specifying
          alternative services, through the use of a JSON object in
          the RESINFO response RR.</t><t>The example in  <xref
          target="ex"></xref> shows what a JSON object might look like
          that specified one or more alternative services. The
          structure of the response is inspired by
          Section 4.4.2 of <xref target="RFC7975"></xref>. </t><t>Note that
          the response includes "glue" RR information to allow the
          alternative service to be accessed without further DNS
          queries, and includes an authenticated domain name to be
          used for authenticating the alternative service.
        </t>
        <t>
        <figure align="center" anchor="ex" title="Response Example with Glue RR Information">
          <preamble></preamble>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[{
  "associated-resolvers": {
    "adn": [
      {
        "name": "cpe123.example.net",
        "uri-template": [
          "https://cpe123.example.net/dns-query{?dns}"
        ],
        "a": [
          "192.0.2.1",
          "192.0.2.2"
        ],
        "aaaa": [
          "2001:db8::1",
          "2001:db8::2"
        ],
        "ttl": 3600
      }
    ]
  }
}
]]>
          </artwork>
          <postamble></postamble>
        </figure>
        <vspace blankLines="1" />
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="resource_level" title="Resource-Level Redirect">
      <t>
        Notwithstanding the issues with resource-level redirects
        described in <xref target="redirection_issues"></xref>, this
        section describes a proposal for returning the "glue" RRs
        required to avoid the bootstrapping issue described in that
        section (but not the roundtrip or caching issues).
      </t>

      <t>
        Servers supporting DoH redirect MUST support returning the redirect
        response body mechanism described hereafter.
      <list style="empty">
        <t>
          Note: "MUST" is used here because resolving the redirect name
          using Do53 will fail in some configurations,
          e.g., https://wiki.mozilla.org/Trusted_Recursive_Resolver
          (network.trr.mode=3).
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Concretely, the DoH server returns in the response body a DNS
        response with an 'application/dns-message' media type as specified in
        Section 6 of <xref target="RFC8484"></xref>, containing any A and AAAA
        records for the domain name in the redirect URI, including any
        CNAMEs.
      </t>

      <t>
        For example, if the redirect URI contains the domain name
        "redirect.example.com", and "redirect.example.com" is a CNAME pointing
        to "real.example.com", then an example response body would contain:
      <list style="symbols">
          <t>A CNAME record for "redirect.example.com"</t>

          <t>Any A records for "real.example.com"</t>

          <t>Any AAAA records for "real.example.com"</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This approach is simple; no client or server support of server push
      is required, and it is also more efficient in terms of the amount of
      data transmitted.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        DoH-related security considerations are discussed in Section 9 of
        <xref target="RFC8484"></xref>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Section 9 of <xref target="RFC7838"></xref> describes security
        considerations related to the use of alternate
        services. Relaxing the host authentication requirements would
        certainly warrant additional security considerations.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not request any action from IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Many thanks to Christian Jacquenet, Philippe Fouquart, and Ben
      Schwartz for the comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7231'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7540'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8484'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8310'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7838'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7538'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.pp-add-resinfo'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-httpbis-bcp56bis'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7975'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7719'?>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
